Finding Aid for Department of Communication (University of Michigan) records, 1926-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Chairman's Records 1949-1986
  - Correspondence File 1964-1985
    The Chairman's Correspondence is generally arranged by year or group of years and thereunder alphabetically. Of special note is a 1975 file regarding University of Michigan graduate and Esquire editor Arnold Gingrich (Gingrich's personal papers and the records of Esquire magazine are held by the Bentley Library). In an effort to obtain an honorary degree for Gingrich, several leading literary figures were solicited for their support. Replies were received from individuals such as John Hersey and Norman Mailer.
    - 1964-1967 with Dean Stephen H. Spurr (Box 7)
    - 1968-1975 (Box 7)
    - 1975
      - General (Box 7)
      - About Arnold Gingrich (Box 7)
    - 1976
      - A-M (Box 7)
      - N-Z (Box 7)
      - Rhoda Blecker (1976-1977) (Box 7)
    - 1977
      - General (Box 7)
      - Ronald Kotulak (Box 7)
    - 1978 (Box 7)
    - 1979 (Box 7)
    - 1979-1981 (primarily 1980-1981)
      - A-B (Box 7)
      - C-G (Box 7)
      - H-K (Box 7)
      - L-Z (Box 7)
      - American Statistical Association (Box 8)
      - Russell Sage Foundation (Box 8)
      - Weisman, Eli (Box 8)
    - 1982-1984
      - A-E (Box 8)
      - G-Z (Box 8)
      - Dean's Office (1982-1985) (Box 8)
      - William Porter (1982-1985 (Box 8)
      - Mary Sinclair (Box 8)
  - Topical File 1949-1986
    The Topical File is arranged alphabetically. It is particularly interesting for information about the journalism department's role in the 1979 merger and also for its discussion of the operation of the newly formed Department of Communication. The merger is discussed in some detail through a chronology drawn up by Helen Uete, and supported through quotation from original documents drawn from the journalism department's files and now grouped together as supporting documentation for the chronology. The operation of the new department is detailed through faculty meeting minutes (1980-1986), memos to the faculty from the chairman (1979-1984), and through a strong body of records regarding curriculum decisions (1982-1986).
    - Curriculum
      - Draft Report to Dean undated (Box 8)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 8)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 8)
      - 1986 (Box 8)
      - 1985-1986 undergraduates (Box 8)
    - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1980-1986 (Box 8)
    - Frieze Building Committee 1980 (Box 8)
    - Full Circle Project 1980 (Box 8)
    - Hopwood Festival 1980 (Box 8)
    - LS&A, College of 1979-1985 (Box 8)
    - Memos to Faculty
      - 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Merger Information (1979)
      - Report to Dean 1962-1963 (Box 8)
      - Department Review 1972 (Box 8)
      - Merger 1977-1981 (Box 8)
      - Reorganization Report 1978 (Box 8)
      - Paper by Helen Uete 1986
        - Background File 1977-1983 (Box 8)
    - Newsletter 1981 (Box 8)
    - Reagan, Joey (Box 8)
    - Students, Graduate Students Profile 1949/50-1965/66 (Box 8)
    - Telecommunications Committee circa 1980 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes prints of faculty interns, fellows and guest lecturers and photos of the 1950 fire in Haven Hall.
  - Awards and Certificates (Box 9)
  - Faculty and Staff
    - Groups (Box 9)
    - Portraits (Box 9)
  - Guest Lecturers (Box 9)
  - Haven Hall Fire 1950 (Box 9)
  - Internships (na 9126) (Box 9)
  - Press Club Fellows
    - Groups (na 9127-9128) (Box 9)
    - Portraits (Box 9)
  - Training Fellows (Box 9)
  - Wooding (Prof. Edward) Memorial Bookshelf (Box 9)
- Sound Recording
  - William Stoneman lecture 1969, 5" reel-to-reel tape (Box 9)
- Topical Files
  Records from the John L. Brumm Scholarship Fund comprise the largest portion of the accession, adding important documents about the establishment of the award and its applicants. These documents provide important demographic information about the students applying for and receiving the scholarship and deserve to be examined. The scholarship was named in honor of John L. Brumm who served as the first chairman of the Department of Journalism following its official founding in 1929 (Journalism's roots extend much earlier, dating back to courses offered by Fred Newton Scott before 1900). Also included are photographs of several Brumm scholarship winners.
  Records of the journalism department's Summer Workshops provide information about the organization and sponsors of this long-running educational program for high school students and educators, begun in the 1950s. This material is particularly valuable for its glimpse into journalism training in Michigan's high schools. Also interesting are the records of Michigan newspapers that sponsored students for the workshops.
  - Report: "Journalism at Michigan" (Faculty Advisory Committee on the Department of Communication) 1994 (Box 10)
  - Courses 1974-1986 (Box 10)
  - Journalism Graduate Program 1993-1995 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Interscholastic Press Association
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Program 1971 (Box 10)
    - Photographs (for Fiftieth Anniversary Program) 1971 (Box 10)
  - Scholarships
    - Brumm, John L., Scholarship Fund
      - Applications and awards 1958-1985, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - General 1939-1980 (Box 10)
      - Photographs 1959-1971 (Box 10)
    - Jameson Memorial Shelf 1960-1969 (Box 10)
  - Summer Workshops
    - Budget 1955-1969 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence 1954-1968 (Box 10)
    - General circa 1950-1971, circa 1992 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Newspaper Sponsors (arranged alphabetically) 1957-1968 (Box 10)
    - Newspaper Fund, Inc. (sponsor)
      - Correspondence and reports 1959-1970 (Box 10)
      - Fellows 1960-1964 (Box 10)
Index to Student Internship Files, by Newspaper
Note: As part of their studies in the department of communication, students had the opportunity to work on various Michigan newspapers. Their reports and other papers to the department of communication often include information of interests to researchers of specific newspapers. The materials will be found in the students' internship file (foreign or American). The following is an index by name of newspaper to these files:
Adrian Daily Telegram Rojnik, Albert
Ann Arbor News Bergqvist, Jaakko; Kim, Yong Hyun; Lee, Wono; Patrick, June C.; Soucek, Rudolf H.
Battle Creek Enquirer and News Abdou, Saad EI-Dine; Besselink, Herman
Bay City Times Barison, Alvise
Benton Harbor News- Palladium Rojnik, Albert
Clinton County Republican News (St. Johns) Padel, Gerd
Detroit Free Press Adam, Lefteri
Detroit News Padel, Gerd H.; Rodriquez, Manuel Eduardo
Detroit Times Hanninen, Oliver; Holmes, George; Kim, Yong Hyun; Lee, Wono; Sasaki, Ken-Ichi
Flint Journal Abdou, Saad El-Dine; Azhar, Ali Khan; Besselink, Herman; Gapper, S. Gordon; Greiss, Louis; Holmes, George; Lee, Wono; Neal, Jack C.; Padel, Gerd H.; Rojnik, Albert; Sasaki, Ken-Ichi
Grand Haven Daily Tribune. Bailyn, Inez Persson; Cain, Stephen; Reynolds, Richard
Grand Rapids Herald Besselink, Herman; Chakravorti, Robindra
Grand Rapids Press Azhar Ali Kahn; Kaul, Donald
Holland Evening Sentinel Azhar, Ali Khan; Besselink, Herman; Chakravorti, Robindra; Elliot, Eleanor; Lee, Wono; Rojnik, Albert
Ionia Sentinel Standard Gapper, S. Gordon
Kalamazoo Gazette Gapper, S. Gordon
Lansing State Journal Griess, Louis; Holmes, George; Kim, Yong Hyun; Rodriquez, Manuel Eduardo
Niles Daily Star Gongwer, Sharon
Owosso Argus Press Bergqvist, Jaakko; Bow, James; Elly, Edward; Reynolds, Roy; Stumpf, Hanns
Pontiac Press Padel, Gerd H.
Port Huron Times Herald Peterson, Kenneth L.; Sasaki, Ken Ichi
Royal Oak Daily Tribune. Chakravorti, Robindra; Rodriquez, Manuel Eduardo
Saginaw News Chapin, Darlene; Griess, Louis; Kim, Yong Hyun
Sault Ste. Marie Evening News. Yacoub, George